A Guide to the Near East Foundation records, Accession 2010:002, RG 2 FA1305
Rockefeller Archive Center
Near East Foundation records, Accession 2010:002, RG 2
1915-2005
Rockefeller Archive Center
Near East Foundation
Near East Relief (Organization)
FA1305
16.34 Cubic Feet 12 standard record storage boxes, 1 letter document box, and 1 oversize photo box holding at-risk materials
The Near East Foundation records, Accessions 2009:104, RG 2 (FA1305) contains 12 standard storage boxes, 1 document box, and one oversize photo box of bound volumes. Some boxes include folders of mixed materials the donor included with particular volumes at the time of accessioning.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged item may be restricted at the discretion of RAC. The bound volume in box 14 will require assistance from an archivist.
Separated Materials
Library materials have been separated from the body of the collection and are available via RAC's library.
Arrangement
As received.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2010 by the Near East Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2010:002.
Biographical / Historical
Cleveland H. Dodge and a group of New York philanthropists formed the Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief in 1915 (as a response to American Ambassador to the Ottoman Empire Henry Morgenthau's plea for assistance). The Committee was chartered by the U.S. Congress as "Near East Relief" (NER) in 1919.
John D. Rockefeller Sr. was one of the first major contributors to the NER. During World War I, the NER is credited with saving 1 million lives of Armenians, Assyrians, Arabs and Persians. From 1915-1930, the NER raised $110 million for refugees. Among its accomplishments, the NER: fed 12 million people; built 40 hospitals; and housed, fed and educated 132,000 children in orphanages and provided them with medical care.
In 1930, Near East Relief officially changed its name to the Near East Foundation and refocused its activities, beyond refugee relief, to become the first international development organization with the objective of catalyzing long-term sustainability through vocational education, training and agricultural programs including experimental projects and instruction.
NEF identifies local communities in need of development assistance, and mobilizes them into grassroots civil society organizations that work to create homegrown solutions to the community's problems.
NEF staff is native members of the communities that they work in. They help guide the people of the community through stages of problem-solving, effective collaboration, and the formation of responsive civil society organizations to develop self-sustaining activities, programs and long-term societies. NEF commonly operates in active yet unstable settlements. These communities are generally beyond the emergency relief stage, yet they need systemic development assistance to build stability and facilitate their long-term survival. NEF operates in Albania, Bulgaria, Greece, Egypt, Lebanon, Mali, Morocco, Sudan, Syria, and throughout the Middle East and Africa.
The NEF's "self-help" approach created the models for the Marshall Plan, Truman's Point-4 Program, the Peace Corp, the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) and the United Nations Development Program (UNDP).
Scope and Contents
This record group primarily consists of dockets, minutes and reports of Near East Relief (NER) and the Near East Foundation (NEF). Materials pertaining to Near East Relief date from 1915 to roughly 1932, while materials pertaining to the Near East Foundation date from roughly 1932 to 2005. A majority of the materials were generated by and for New York-based personnel, and document executive-level decision making. However, information on day-to-day foreign operations can be found in the dockets, which include reports that reference foundation-operated orphanages and schools. Those interested in visual sources can look to the issues of the "New Near East" newletter, 1922 to 1924, and the "Bulletin of the Near East Society", 1952-1955.
Related Materials
Near East Foundation records, Accessions 2009:104, RG 1 (FA406)
Near East Foundation records, Accession 2010:020, RG 3 (FA1306)
Near East Foundation records, Audiovisual Materials, RG 4 (FA1307)
Near East Foundation records, Accession 2012:060, RG 5 (FA1308)
Near East Foundation records, Fred and Carrie Midgley papers, Accession 2012:071, RG 6 (FA1309)
- Near East Foundation records, Accession 2010:002, 1915-2005; 2; Near East Foundation; Near East Relief (Organization); 16.04 Cubic Feet 12 standard record storage boxes and one document box
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Near East Foundation collection was officially donated to Rockefeller Archive Center by Charles Benjamin, NEF President, June 2011.
  Records were received as Accession 2010:002.
  - American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief: Minutes, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief: Index to Minutes, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1919-1920; Minutes of the meetings of: Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, and Finance Committee. Includes index and appropriations. (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1920-1921; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, Finance Committee, and Special Committee. Includes list of appropriations and index. (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1922-1923; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Board of Trustees, Finance Committee, and Executive Committee. Includes list of appropriations and index. (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1924-1925; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Board of Trustees, Industrial Committee, and Executive Committee. Includes list of appropriations and index. (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1926-1928; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees. Includes list of appropriations and index. (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1928-1929; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Conservation Committee (A Sub Committee of the Executive Committee) (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1929-1930; Includes minutes of the meetings of: Conservation Committee (A Sub Committee of the Executive Committee) (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1929-1930; Includes the minutes of the meetings of: Program Committee of the Conservation Committee (Box 1)
  - General Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1919-1944 (Box 1)
  - Near East Relief: Dockets, 1929-1930; Dockets for the annual meetings of: Board of Trustees and Executive Committee (Box 2)
  - Near East Relief: Dockets, 1931-1932; Dockets for annual meetings of: Board of Trustees and Executive Committee (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1930; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1931; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1932; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1930-1934; Minutes of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1931-1934; Overseas staff reports to the New York office (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1930-1940; Minutes for the meetings of: Program Committee (Box 2)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1933; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1934; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1935; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1936; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1937; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1938; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1939; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Near East Relief: Dockets, 1933-1936; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors and Executive Committee (Box 3)
  - Near East Relief: Minutes, 1929-1936; Minutes for the meetings of: Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees (Box 3)
  - Near East Foundation: Basic Project Reports, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Near East Relief: Dockets, 1937-1944; Dockets for the annual meetings of: Board of Trustees (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1940; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1941; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1942; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1943; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1939-1942; Annual Reports of Laird Archer, Foreign Director (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1935-1939; Minutes of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1940-1945; Minutes of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1935-1939; Annual reports of Laird Archer, Foreign Director. 1 of 2 copies. (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1935-1939; Annual reports of Laird Archer, Foreign Director. 2 of 2 copies. (Box 4)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1944; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1945; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1946-1947; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1948-1949; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1943-1946; Annual reports of Laird Archer, Foreign Director (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1946-1950; Minutes of the meetings of: Board of Directors. Includes table of contents with vote numbers and topic. (Box 5)
  - Essay: Building a Farm School Curriculum for Training the Sons of Albanian Farmers, 1940; Written by Ralph Herbert Allee. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence File: Ralph H. Allee and H.B. Allen, 1949; Correspondence between Ralph H. Allen, Director of Inter-American Institute for Agricultural Sciences and H.B. Allen, Near East Foundation Educational Director (Box 5)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1950; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1951; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1952; Dockets of the Meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1953-1954; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1946-1956; Annual reports of H.B. Allen, Educational Director. The 1950 report is missing from this volume, but can found in Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1947-1950 in box 5. (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1951-1954; Minutes of the meetings of:Board of Directors. Includes index with vote number and topic. (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1951-1956; Annual reports of H.B. Allen, Educational Director (Box 6)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1955-1956; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1957-1958; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1959-1960; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1961-1963; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1964-1965; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 7)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1966-1967; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1968-1969; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1966-1970; Minutes of Corporation, Board of Driectors, and Executive Committee Meetings. Includes index of votes and topic. (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1959-1965; Minutes of Corporation, Board of Driectors, and Executive Committee Meetings. Includes index of votes (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Annual Reports, 1961-1977; Pamphlets for distribution (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1970-1971; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1972-1973; Dockets of the Meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 8)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1974-1975; Dockets of the Meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 9)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1976-1977; Dockets of the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 9)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1978-1979; Dockets of the Meetings of: Board of Directors. (Box 9)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1971-1975; Minutes of Corporation, Board of Driectors, and Executive Committee Meetings. Includes index of votes (Box 9)
  - Near East Foundation: Minutes, 1976-1980; Minutes of Corporation, Board of Driectors, and Executive Committee Meetings. Includes index of votes (Box 9)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1980-1981; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 9)
  - Minutes: Near East Foundation v. William E. Boyland, January 8, 1951; Minutes of case New York Supreme Court case "to exempt [the Near East Foundation's] property... on the ground that the Near East Foundation is a charitable, educational and scientific corporation." (Box 10)
  - Plan for Employee's Benefit Fund of Near East Foundation, 1945-1950 (Box 10)
  - Plan for Employee's Benefit Fund-Mixed Materials, 1947-1962 (Box 10)
  - Near East Foundation: Audits, 1930-1952 (Box 10)
  - Near East Foundation: Audits, 1953-1974 (Box 10)
  - Near East Foundation: Audits and Financial Statements, 1979-1989 (Box 10)
  - Near East Relief/Foundation: Auditors' Reports, 1922-1944 (Box 10)
  - Near East Relief: Auditors' Reports, 1917-1922 (Box 10)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1982-1983; Minutes for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 11)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1984-1985; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 11)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1986-1987; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 11)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1988-1989; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 11)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1990-1991; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 11)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1992-1993; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1994-1995; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1996-1997; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 1998-1999; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 2000-2001; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 2002-2003; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - Near East Foundation: Dockets, 2004-2005; Dockets for the meetings of: Board of Directors (Box 12)
  - The New Near East, January-December 1922; Monthly newsletter published by Near East Relief. 1 of 2 copies. (Box 13)
  - The New Near East, January-December 1922; Monthly newsletter published by Near East Relief. 2 of 2 copies (Box 13)
  - The New Near East, January-December 1923; Monthly newsletter published by Near East Relief (Box 13)
  - The New Near East, January-December 1924; Newsletter published by Near East Relief. (Box 13)
  - Bulletin of the Near East Society, March 1952-December 1953; Monthly newsletter published by the Near East Society, an organization sponsored by the Near East Foundation and the Near East College Association. (Box 13)
  - Bulletin of the Near East Society, January 1954-December 1955; Monthly newsletter published by the Near East Society, an organization sponsored by the Near East Foundation and the Near East College Association. (Box 13)
  - Near East Relief: Foreign Area Accounting Manual, 1925 (Box 14)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Volume suffers from red rot. See archivist for assistance.